Guide to the Peter Viereck papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Correspondence, 1926-2005
  - Subseries I.2: Institutions and Subjects, 1936-2005
    - Correspondence with Editors and Publishers, 1953-2005 (Box 7, 20, 23, 26, 44-45, 77, 87, 89, 94-98, 111, 113)
    - Correspondence with Editors Promoting Metapolitics, 2002 (Box 18)
- Series II: Research Notes and Clippings, 1815-2005
  Series II is composed of newspaper clippings and documents related to Viereck's interests. Some of the more widely researched topics include Russian History, prominent Russian politicians, Conservatism, Marxism and Socialism, Nazis, German History and politics.
  - Annotated Articles, 1941-1979 (Box 12, 13)
  - Annotated Poetry Articles, undated (Box 9, 13)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1970s (Box 47)
  - Austria, 1943-1948 (Box 114)
  - Babbitt, Irving, 1978 (Box 65)
  - Babbitt, Cabot, 1955 (Box 65)
  - Beirut, 1960s (Box 98)
  - Beirut Laws, 1960s (Box 98)
  - Bertram, Ernst, undated (Box 26)
  - Bismarck Lecture, circa 1980s (Box 102)
  - Blumberg, Phillip, circa 1980s (Box 103)
  - Boris Pasternak, 1958-1989 (Box 11, 12, 55, 89)
  - Brecht, Bertolt, 1970-1980 (Box 113)
  - Britain and the Bourgeoisie, 1970s (Box 102)
  - British Empire, 1950s, undated (Box 102)
  - British Heritage, undated (Box 102)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, 1980s (Box 103)
  - Brooklyn Bridge, 1980s (Box 36)
  - Bukharin, Nikolai, 1960s-1980s (Box 107)
  - Celan, Paul, 1981-1996, undated (Box 113)
  - Chakovsky, Alexander, 1960s (Box 44)
  - Churchill, Winston, undated (Box 102)
  - Coins, 1978 (Box 111)
  - Cold War, 1940s-1980s (Box 104)
  - Conservatism Articles, 1960s (Box 107, 117)
  - Conservatism Articles by Claes Ryn, 1979-1989 (Box 37-38)
  - Corruption in Russia, 1991 (Box 35)
  - Crane, Hart, undated (Box 3)
  - Crimean War--Post 1848, undated (Box 104)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1965-1990 (Box 44)
  - Dostoyevsky, 1970s (Box 46)
  - Eckart, 1925-1984 (Box 113)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1953, undated (Box 110)
  - England
    - Class Conflict, 1832-1884 (Box 102)
    - Victorian Era, undated (Box 102)
    - Social Change, undated (Box 102)
    - Social Legacy, undated (Box 103)
    - Social Life, 1950s (Box 102)
    - After World War II, circa 1960s (Box 102)
  - Europe, 1980s-1990s (Box 104)
  - Evtushenko, 1962 (Box 108)
  - Fascism, 1953, undated (Box 103-104)
  - Fascism and Communism, circa 1950s, undated (Box 105)
  - Faust, undated (Box 19)
  - Feminism, 1980s (Box 44)
  - Field, Andrew--"Abram Tertz's Ordeal by Mirror," 1965 (Box 106)
  - For "Shame and Glory," 1961 (Box 110)
  - France
    - Background, 1970s (Box 102)
    - 1815-1848, 1970s (Box 102)
    - 1885-1914, 1980s (Box 102)
    - 1919-1948, circa 1950s (Box 102)
  - French Revolution, circa 1970s, undated (Box 102)
  - French Society--1870-1914, undated (Box 102)
  - Frost, Robert, 1960s (Box 76)
  - Germany
    - 1815-1848, undated (Box 102)
    - 1870-1914, undated (Box 102)
    - 1980s (Box 102)
    - Benn, Gottfried, undated (Box 113)
    - Boll, Heinrich, 1984-1986 (Box 113)
    - Expressionist Prints, 1983 (Box 113)
    - Industry--1870-1914, undated (Box 102)
    - Weimar, undated, 1970s (Box 102)
    - In World War I--Background, undated (Box 102)
    - Social Democratic Party--1920s, undated (Box 102)
    - Weimar--1930-1933, undated (Box 102)
    - Nazis, undated (Box 102, 113)
    - Nazis and Students, 1980s (Box 102)
    - Post-1945, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 102)
    - Terrorism in, 1970s (Box 47)
    - General, undated (Box 113)
  - God and the Basket Cases, 1967 (Box 55)
  - Goldstucker, Eduard, circa 1960s (Box 46)
  - Greek Revolt--1821-1829, undated (Box 102)
  - Hapsburg--1848, undated (Box 102)
  - Hapsburg--1870-1914, undated (Box 102)
  - Haushofer, Karl, 1940s (Box 45)
  - Herzen, Alexander, 1968 (Box 46)
  - Hitler, 1970s-1980s (Box 45, 102)
  - Hitler's Cold War, 1930s-1970s (Box 102)
  - Hoddis, Jakob van, undated (Box 45)
  - Hugo Von Hofmannsthal, undated (Box 45)
  - Hungary, 1960s (Box 46)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, 1952 (Box 43)
  - Italy--1815-1848, undated (Box 103)
  - Italy--1870-1914, circa 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 103)
  - Italy--Post-War, circa 1960s (Box 103)
  - Italy--Unification of, 1849-1870, undated (Box 103)
  - Junger, Ernst, 1993 (Box 47)
  - Kastner, Erich circa 1940s (Box 45)
  - Kazakov, Yuri and Review of His Book, Wanders Along the Volga, 1964 (Box 46)
  - Khrushcev, Nikita, 1950s (Box 107)
  - Koestler, Arthur, undated (Box 90)
  - Kolakowski, Leszek, undated (Box 45)
  - Lenin, 1964-1980 (Box 106)
  - Leonov, Leonid, undated (Box 36)
  - Lermontov, circa 1981-1984 (Box 106)
  - Lukacs, 1963-1971 (Box 106)
  - Mandelstan, Nadezhda, 1966-1982 (Box 106)
  - Marshak, Samuel, 1966, undated (Box 106)
  - Marxism, Socialism, and Russian and Soviet History, undated (Box 8, 9, 44-46, 56)
  - Maxim Gorky, 1970s (Box 46)
  - Maximin, undated (Box 26)
  - Mayakovsky, 1970-1986 (Box 106)
  - Mehemet Ali Crisis, undated (Box 102)
  - Medvedev, Roy, 1960s-1970s (Box 107)
  - Milosz, Czelaw, 1988-1990, undated (Box 106)
  - Modern Poetry, 1966 (Box 37)
  - Napoleon III, 1970s (Box 102)
  - Nationalism--Europe, 1940s-1950s (Box 103)
  - The New York Times, 1970s-1980s (Box 49)
  - Nietzsche, undated (Box 77, 114)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1970s (Box 48)
  - Notes on Essay "Anti-Form or Neo," undated (Box 43)
  - Orwell, George, 1980s (Box 104)
  - Palindromes, 2002 (Box 49)
  - Papal Policy After 1870, undated (Box 103)
  - "Period Between the Wars"--1919-1939, 1980s (Box 102)
  - Poetic Structure, 1970s-1990s (Box 14)
  - Poets and the Industrial Age, circa 1970s (Box 26)
  - Pogodin, 1965 (Box 106)
  - Poland, July 1962 (Box 98)
  - Poland--Brief, 1962 (Box 98)
  - Poland--Notes About Trips, 1962 (Box 98)
  - Political History, undated (Box 10)
  - Population Dynamics, circa 1980s (Box 103)
  - Populism, 1974-1975 (Box 65)
  - Privacy in the United States, 1974 (Box 107)
  - Religion, undated (Box 32, 65)
  - Rhythm, undated (Box 14)
  - Rilke, Rainer, 1980s-1990s (Box 47)
  - Romanian Trip, 1964 (Box 97)
  - Rome, undated (Box 103)
  - Rozhdestvensky, Robert, 1963, undated (Box 106)
  - Russia
    - 1860-1914, undated (Box 104)
    - History, 1960s-1980s (Box 10, 35, 55, 66, 76, 92, 102-103)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 43)
    - Language, Study, and Harvard Grade, circa 1940s (Box 106)
    - Leaders, circa 1960s, undated (Box 107)
    - Law, undated (Box 106)
    - Populism in the 19th Century, 1978 (Box 106)
  - Schmidt, Carl, 1980s (Box 44)
  - Shakespeare, undated (Box 1)
  - "Shame and Glory"--Sources, 1950s (Box 110)
  - Sholokhov, Mikhail, 1967-1979 (Box 106)
  - Sinyavsky Talks Back, 1966 (Box 106)
  - Slang, undated (Box 19)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Alexander, 1970s-1980s (Box 50-51, 106-107)
  - Sosnora, Viktor, undated (Box 105)
  - Soviet Union
    - General, 1963-1970 (Box 108)
    - Dissidence and Détente, 1973-1974 (Box 10)
    - Dissidents, 1980s (Box 46)
    - Soviet-Nazi Relations, undated (Box 44)
    - Slave Labor, 1951-1953 (Box 106)
  - Spear, Albert, 1971 (Box 65)
  - Stalin, 1958-1986, undated (Box 44, 107)
  - Stauffenberg, Hans Christoph Baron von, 1960s-1970s (Box 66)
  - Student Protests, 1960s-1970s (Box 10)
  - Suicide, 1970s (Box 107)
  - Swinburne, undated (Box 1)
  - Tarsis, Valery, 1956-1966 (Box 106)
  - Theodor Storm, circa 1960s (Box 45)
  - "Third Rome" Concept, 1970s (Box 37, 55)
  - Tvardivsky, Aleksandr, 1961-1972 (Box 106)
  - Uzbekistan and Siberia, 1975-1976 (Box 106)
  - Vienna--Congress of, 1980s (Box 103)
  - Vietnam--Annotated Clippings, 1970s (Box 65)
  - Voznesensky, Andrei, 1960s-1970s (Box 105)
  - Wall St, 1960s (Box 105)
  - Women and Poetry, 1980s (Box 3)
  - World and Russian History, undated (Box 41-42, 49-50)
  - World War I
    - 1980s (Box 103)
    - Alliances of, undated (Box 103)
    - And the Balkan Crisis--1907-1914, undated (Box 103)
    - Peace Treaties--Versailles 1919, undated (Box 103)
  - World War II, 1943-1961 (Box 103, 114)
  - Yakobson, Anatoly, circa 1973 (Box 106)
  - Yeats, William Butler, undated (Box 76)
  - Yevtushenko, Yevgeny, 1962-1995 (Box 107-108)
  - Zaiunchikovsky, Petrovich, 1962 (Box 106)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 102, 106, 111,119)
- Series III: Drafts and Outlines, 1930s-2001
  Series III contains drafts for Viereck's poems, essays, articles, and books. The series also has a small amount of reviews written by Viereck as well as lectures and some translations. Records are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - 1984 Was Wrong, 1966 (Box 72)
  - "Alsace-Lorraine, 1871-1914 and German-French Relations"--Chapter 5, undated (Box 102)
  - "The Amateur Hour," undated (Box 107)
  - "Anti-Form or Neo: A Curse on Both House," 1993 (Box 108)
  - "Anti-Semitism and the German Problem," 1985, undated (Box 113)
  - "Anyhow," undated (Box 101)
  - Applewood
    - Discards, 1968-1977 (Box 100)
    - "Honored Guest," 1969-1975 (Box 100)
    - "Salt," 1972-1974 (Box 100)
    - New Revised Edition, 1980 (Box 118)
  - Archer in the Marrow: The Applewood Cycles, 1971-1985 (Box 17, 40, 61-62, 64, 76, 91-92, 94, 96, 108, 117)
  - "Arethusa: The First Morning", 1951 (Box 80, 101)
  - At My Hospital Window, 1991 (Box 75-76, 117)
  - Backtalk, undated (Box 117)
  - Balkins--1900-1980, undated (Box 102)
  - Before the Hunt, undated (Box 81)
  - "Bernard Shaw's Personal Message to the Youth of America"--with Correspondence, 1930s, undated (Box 105)
  - "Better a Real Huckster Than a False Sensitive Plant," 1954 (Box 103)
  - "The Biology of Poetry," undated (Box 94)
  - "Birth of Song" (or "Some Lines in Three Parts"), 1964 (Box 101)
  - "Poetry and the Book Awards: A Plastic Parnassus?" 1980 (Box 11)
  - "Transplanter Credo," undated (Box 7)
  - "A Touch of Poet" By Deborah Kearney With Poems by Viereck, 2000 (Box 4, 6)
  - "Cabot Babbitt: A Post-Modern of the New Conservatism," undated (Box 103-104)
  - "Cautious Optimism versus Suicidal Optimism," circa 1960 (Box 44)
  - "Churchill and Cripps: a Study in Witchcraft," 1950s (Box 103)
  - "Clio is Not Cleo: The Messiness of History"--Transcript of Final Lecture to Students, 1997 (Box 5)
  - "Conclusion: One Kind of Conservative Viewpoint for 1985-2000," 1985 (Box 14, 15)
  - Conclusions, circa 1960s (Box 44)
  - "Conservatism," undated (Box 104, 107)
  - Conservatism--Author Preface, undated (Box 104)
  - Conservatism Revisited, 1960s-1980s (Box 6, 28-29, 32-33, 56, 103)
  - Conservatism Revisited, 1962 (Includes Reviews) (Box 28-29)
  - Conservatism Revisited (Expanded), 1950s (Box 103)
  - Conservatism: From John Adams to Churchill, 1985 (Box 56, 94)
  - "Conservatives and Non-Marxist, Socialists: Two Semi-Compatibles," undated (Box 104)
  - Context for "George's Park," "Hellingrath," "George's Jewish Disciples," undated (Box 99)
  - Continuities, 1980s (Box 98, 117)
  - "Core" Cycle--Epilogue, undated (Box 108)
  - Counter-Continuities, undated (Box 117)
  - Creative Conservatism--"Ending the Youth Secession," 1970s (Box 104, 111)
  - Cycle Two--"Hacked," undated (Box 108)
  - Cycle Six--"Rogue," undated (Box 108)
  - "Czernin's Duel with Germany for a 'Tolerable' Peace," undated (Box 93)
  - Dance of the Haemophiliacs, 1960s (Box 98)
  - "Decorum," undated (Box 108)
  - "Der Ditcher im Zeitalter der Maschine," undated (Box 46)
  - "Dies Irae, Dies Illa," 1932 (Box 101)
  - "The Dignity of Lyricism," undated (Box 103-104)
  - "Dionysus in Old Age", 1987-1991 (Box 95, 117)
  - "Direct Democracy: From Left-Wing to Right-Wing Populism," undated (Box 104)
  - "Disturber, Restorer," Poetry Now, 1982 (Box 91, 95, 108)
  - Door, 2000-2003 (Box 5, 19, 43, 104, 117)
  - "Dramatis Personae," undated (Box 101)
  - "Ending the Youth Secession: Take Conservatism Away From Reagan's Conservatives," undated (Box 107)
  - "On the Engineering Project for a Tunnel Under the English Channel," undated (Box 103)
  - "English Verse: A Technical History," undated (Box 14)
  - "The Enlightened Despots," undated (Box 103)
  - Europe, undated (Box 102)
  - European Society of 1870, undated (Box 102)
  - Fascism Revisited, 1950, undated (Box 107)
  - "Feelings," undated (Box 107)
  - "Fiftieth Birthday," 1966 (Box 101)
  - The First Morning, undated (Box 42)
  - "For a Third Force in Poetry," undated (Box 103)
  - "Form in Poetry: Would Jacob Wrestle with a Flabby Angel?" undated (Box 16)
  - "Fourteen Common Faults in Poetry," undated (Box 103)
  - France on the Papacy, undated (Box 102)
  - "Freedom and the Intellectuals in Russia today", circa 1960s (Box 55)
  - "The Frontier behind the Forehead," undated (Box 86, 107)
  - "German Unity, Stein Versus Metternich," undated (Box 45)
  - "Germany's Future: Shedding the Nazi Heritage," undated (Box 113)
  - "God: a Theological Cabaret," 1967 November (Box 101)
  - "God" Notes, 1968 November (Box 101)
  - "God and the Basketcases," 1960s (Box 101)
  - "Green Mass," 1970, undated (Box 100, 108-109)
  - "History and the Conservative Secret," undated (Box 104)
  - "Hospital Window"--for Joseph Brodsky, 1990 (Box 92-93)
  - "Humphrey's Stanza--new longer version, 1968 (Box 101)
  - "Hurrah for Karamazov," undated (Box 111)
  - "ID LIB," 1975-1978 (Box 9)
  - "If I Were Emperor!" undated (Box 118)
  - "In Earth Who Wallows Like its Borrowers?" 1950s (Box 101)
  - "Inner Liberty: The Stubborn Grit in the Machine," undated (Box 36)
  - "Inwardness: the Dimension Behind the Forehead," undated (Box 107)
  - "Ironic Reflection on a Monarchist Republic From John Alame to Reagan," undated (Box 117)
  - "Ivan the Terrible Rides Again," undated (Box 44, 67)
  - Just Now, 1965-1976 (Box 108)
  - "Killed by a Car at 21," undated (Box 101)
  - "Last Vigil"--Discards, undated (Box 99)
  - "Lest We Forget: An Appeal to the American People," undated (Box 103)
  - "Letter from a Toe", 1974-1975 (Box 100)
  - "Lost Self"--dedicated to John Alexis Viereck, 1993 (Box 117)
  - "Lot's Wife," undated (Box 117)
  - "The Lyricism of the Weak," undated (Box 101)
  - "Lyric," 1955 (Box 101)
  - "Marxists and Conservatives: Two Incompatible Cultures," undated (Box 104)
  - Metapolitics, undated (Box 19-20, 100, 104, 117)
  - Metapolitics--Notes and Clippings on Wagner (Box 18-20, 35)
  - "Metternich: The Conservative Way to Freedom"--Bound Dissertation, 1930s (Box 69)
  - "The Mob Within the Heart: A New Russian Revolution," undated (Box 104, 106, 108, 110)
  - "De Monarchia," undated (Box 104)
  - Morality--Changes between the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries, undated (Box 102)
  - "The Muse and the Machine: Impact of Industrialism on Poets and on Humanity," undated (Box 76, 95)
  - "The New Cultural Blues," undated (Box 104-105)
  - "A New Edition of Pares' Russia"--New York Times, 1947 (Box 106)
  - A New Russian Revolution: Mob Within the Heart--Includes Annotated Press Clippings and Correspondence, 1960s (Box 28, 54, 63)
  - "New Science" Lecture Outlines, undated (Box 103)
  - Neovulgarian Blues--Song, 1959-1960 (Box 61)
  - Nineteenth Century--Problems of and Outline, undated (Box 102)
  - "The Non-Marxist (Conservative-Ethical) Case Against Nazism," undated (Box 104)
  - "Not IBM Cards: the Same Conservative Revolt in Russia and America," undated (Box 107)
  - "Not IBM Cards"--Discards and Drafts, undated (Box 107)
  - "Not IBM Cards"--Extras, undated (Box 107)
  - "Observing the Observer," undated (Box 46)
  - "Ode," undated (Box 101)
  - "Ode to Joy," 1962 (Box 101)
  - "Ogling Through Ice: The Sullen Lyricism of Georg Heym," 1971 (Box 15, 16)
  - "OPCOMP"--Play/Poem, 1967-1977, 1993 (Box 23, 25, 38-40, 78)
  - "Our Conservative Roots," undated (Box 14, 15)
  - "The Parallel Youth Revolt in America and Russia," undated (Box 105)
  - "Part One Waltz"--Long Magazine Version, undated (Box 100)
  - Part Three: Heym, undated (Box 104)
  - "Pavlov's Dog Won't Salivate: A Poet and Historian Visits the Soviet Union," undated (Box 106)
  - The Persimmon Tree, undated (Box 42)
  - "Pish," undated (Box 117)
  - "Poetry and the Modern World"--Lecture, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Preface: "A Message: Moderates of the World Unite," undated (Box 106)
  - "Pure Form?: The Pound Controversy Revisited," undated (Box 16)
  - Analysis of Red Brigades Communique, 1980s (Box 104)
  - "Report on Harvard Class of '37," undated (Box 19)
  - "The Revolution in Values: Roots of the European Catastrophe, 1870-1952," undated (Box 104)
  - Rise of Russia--1796, undated (Box 103)
  - ROM Love--18th and 19th centuries, undated (Box 104)
  - "Rossetti Serenade"--Discards, 1969-1970 (Box 100)
  - "Round," undated (Box 8, 13)
  - Russia--Lecture, undated (Box 103)
  - The Russians, 1960s (Box 56)
  - Russia's Conspiracy of Feelings, 1965 (Box 74, 107)
  - Shame and Glory--"Bloody-Minded Professors," undated (Box 104, 110)
  - "Snow of Rain," 1966 (Box 101)
  - "Some Three Line Stanzas," undated (Box 101)
  - "Some Walks on the Edge," 1960s (Box 27, 42, 82)
  - "Soviet Censorship: The Moral Blight," circa 1960 (Box 44)
  - "The Statist Line", 1950 (Box 64)
  - "Staying Human in the Machine Age," undated (Box 111)
  - "Stefan George Reconsidered," 1987 (Box 16, 45)
  - "The Coming of American National Socialism," undated (Box 23)
  - "The Ezra Pound Celebrations: Some Qualms," 1985 (Box 9)
  - "The Muse and the Machine," undated (Box 14, 26)
  - New and Selected Poems, 1967 (Box 54, 59, 64, 78)
  - New Views on Metternich, 1951 (Box 114)
  - "Old Fool, Die Quicker," 1993 (Box 117)
  - Opcomp, undated (Box 78, 100)
  - "Oxford is a Hotbed of Tradition," 1983, undated (Box 111)
  - "The Poet in the Machine Age", 1949 (Box 83)
  - "The Poetry of Thomas Ferril," 1954 (Box 3)
  - "Politics versus Poetry: In Yeats, Pound, Stefan George," undated (Box 76)
  - "The Polity of Walther Von Der Vogelweide," circa 1930s (Box 44)
  - "Post-Nazi Guilt Feelings"--With Articles, 1960-1964, undated (Box 113)
  - "Pound, Williams and the Road not Taken," 1986 (Box 95)
  - "Red-Handed," undated (Box 117)
  - "Roll Call," undated (Box 109)
  - "Salt," undated (Box 108)
  - "Secret America," undated (Box 104)
  - "Shame and Glory," undated (Box 110)
  - "Six Half-Rhymes of the Act of Tough," undated (Box 103)
  - "Some Refrains at the Charles River"--Phi Beta Kappa Poem, 1953 (Box 89, 117)
  - "Staying Human in the Machine Age," circa 1977 (Box 107)
  - "Strict Form in Poetry," undated (Box 107)
  - "Sublime Unwashedness," 1937-1947 (Box 110)
  - "Take Conservatism Away From the Conservatism," 1952 (Box 104, 108)
  - "The Templars"--Drafts, 1970s, undated (Box 99)
  - "The Temporary Ivory Tower" or "For Whom the Bell Doesn't Toll," 1966-1967 (Box 107)
  - Terror and Decorum, 1949 (Box 43, 95)
  - "Three-Act Morality Play," 1950 (Box 111)
  - "Three Basic Concepts in Hegel's Philosophy," undated (Box 102)
  - "Three Line Stanzas," undated (Box 103)
  - Three Sinister Janitors, 1954 (Box 75)
  - "The Third Frontier," undated (Box 103)
  - Tide and Continuities: Last and First Poems, 1980s (Box 62-63, 92-95, 102)
  - "Time Enough," undated (Box 103)
  - "Thin Ice," circa 1978 (Box 103)
  - "To Helen," undated (Box 103)
  - "Today's Revolts against Communism in Eastern Europe," 1990 (Box 35)
  - "The Trained Seal versus the Unadjusted Man: A Decade of New American Poetry," 1954 (Box 103)
  - Transition to the 19th Century (Box 103)
  - Transplantings, 1999 October-2000 December (Box 5, 7, 39-40, 83, 88-89, 117)
  - The Tree Witch--Play, 1961 (Box 29-30, 47, 55-56, 58-60)
  - "The Trial of Joseph Ellis," 2001 (Box 7)
  - "The Trojan Dove: 'Peace' Versus Peace," 1952, undated (Box 110)
  - "Tug of War," undated (Box 103)
  - "Tuscan Loam," undated (Box 103)
  - "Twelve O'Clock" (or "Of Late I Think of Beddoes"), 1966 (Box 101)
  - "The Two Again," 1966 (Box 101)
  - The Unadjusted Man, 1950s-1970s, undated (Box 33, 66, 77, 95, 104, 109-110)
  - "Uncouplets," 1974 (Box 100m 103)
  - "Undertow," 1950s (Box 101)
  - "Unenlightened Despots," undated (Box 103)
  - Unification of Germany and Italy, undated (Box 102)
  - "Up," 1980, undated (Box 117)
  - "The Vaudeville of the Gods," 1960s (Box 101, 109)
  - "Verse," 1960s (Box 101)
  - "Victorian Serenade," 1980s (Box 102)
  - "Victory Ballad of Extinct Race," undated (Box 102)
  - Walks and Trees--Forward, undated (Box 101)
  - "What Can We Learn From History?"--Lecture at Mount Holyoke, undated (Box 102)
  - "Why I Wrote Continuities," undated (Box 117)
  - "Wives," undated (Box 102)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, undated (Box 103, 105-106)
  - Miscellaneous Covers, undated (Box 114)
  - x-Poems for Tide and Continuities, undated (Box 8, 19)
  - Untitled Drafts
    - undated (Box 104, 108-111, 113, 116-117)
    - American Book Awards Speech, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Conservatism Article for Encyclopedia Britannica, 1972 (Box 27, 48)
    - Conservatism Article in Dorothy James's Outside, Looking In, 1971 (Box 27)
    - Essay Drafts, 1930-1957 (Box 23, 64, 81)
    - Essay on Prince Metternich, undated (Box 33)
    - German Romanticism Lecture, undated (Box 47)
    - History of Europe--Chapters on Germany, 1930s (Box 25)
    - History of Germany--Book, circa 1960s (Box 45)
    - Honors Day Participants Address, Brooklyn College, 1951 November 14 (Box 14)
    - Juvenilia, undated (Box 76)
    - Poems, undated (Box 104, 113)
    - Ronald Reagan Article, 1980 (Box 57)
    - T.S. Elliot Article, undated (Box 2)
    - Vachel Lindsay, Vachel--Essays and Lectures, circa 1980 (Box 20, 28-29, 32)
  - Multiple Drafts
    - Pieces on Russia, undated (Box 8, 64-69, 71-74)
    - Archer In The Marrow, 1987 (Box 118)
    - Articles and Notes on Other Poets, undated (Box 1-6)
    - Essay Drafts about Conservatism, 1930s-1970s (Box 24, 78, 80, 83, 92, 94)
    - Essays on Ezra Pound, 1950s-1980s (Box 36-37)
    - Essays (and Poems), undated (Box 12, 13, 72, 91, 105, 108, 114, 117)
    - Poems in German, undated (Box 45, 47, 117)
    - Poems, undated, 1970s-1980s (Box 1-9, 11-18, 28-29, 32-34, 47-49, 55-62, 64-65, 67, 71-72, 75-77, 80-84, 88-93, 95, 97-100, 111, 117)
  - Reviews by Viereck
    - Book and Poetry Reviews, 1941-1967, undated (Box 2, 27, 54, 56-57, 103, 114)
    - Review of "For the Good of the Cause" by Alexander Solzhenitsyn, 1964 (Box 107)
    - Review of "The Irony of American History" by Reinhold Niebuhr, 1952 April 6 (Box 18)
    - Review of Life of Lenin by Louis Fischer, 1964 (Box 44)
    - Review of Observations of Abnormality in Literature and Politics By Russell Kirk (Box 5, 6)
    - Review of Russia's Educational Heritage By William H.E. Johnson, undated (Box 44)
  - Translations
    - Transplantings, undated (Box 104)
    - Stefan George, undated, 1980s (Box 53-57, 78, 82-83, 88-89, 94, 96, 103, 117)
    - Goethe--Poems, undated (Box 113)
    - Heym, undated (Box 39, 43, 47, 55, 78, 88-90, 96)
    - Hofmannsthal, Hugo Von--Poems, 1976, undated (Box 113)
    - Adam Wazyk, "Niewiedza," undated (Box 105)
    - Yevgeny Yevtushenko, "Babi Yar," undated (Box 107)
    - Translations of Viereck's Work, 1940s-1960s (Box 103)
    - Russian Translations, 1963 (Box 66, 73, 89)
    - German Translations, undated (Box 78)
    - German Translation of "Double Star: The Oscillating Orbits of Stefan George & Georg Heym," 1980s (Box 118)
    - "The Turning Year," "Cain the Beautiful," 1964-1965 (Box 101)
  - Published Work (Box 121)
- Series IV: Reviews and Criticism of Viereck's Work, 1940s-2003
  Series IV holds reviews of Viereck's writings. These reviews are of both his books and collections of his poems. This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Archer in the Marrow, 1992 (Box 108)
  - Conservatism Revisited, 1940s-1970s (Box 103, 104, 110)
  - Conservative Manifesto, 1970s (Box 111)
  - New Conservatism, 1954 (Box 110)
  - New and Selected Poems, 1970s (Box 1)
  - The First Morning, 1950 (Box 1, 3, 14)
  - The Persimmon Tree, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Shame and Glory, 1953-1983, undated (Box 111)